<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>LogServ Manual</title>

  <para>Welcome to the LogServ Manual. This document will aid you in setting
  up and running LogServServ on your IRC network.</para>

  <para>LogServ is a basic Channel Logging Module for the NeoStats Services
  that can log channel activity to a log file for processing by 3rd party
  programs such as Onis or MircStats. These programs can then produce HTML
  pages with interesting statistics on the channel activities. </para>

  <para>LogServ is flexible in the logging of channels, and can produce log
  files in the same format as Xchat, Mirc, EggDrop, or our own custom logging
  format, meaning you should be able to use just about any IRC Log Parsing
  program to produce statistics for you.</para>

  <para>Additionally, LogServ can rotate log files based on log file size or
  age, and place them in a different directory for processing at any time.</para>

  <para>We recomend that you use the Onis Log file parser, as its what we have
  done our testing with, and additionally, has several neat features that are
  applicable to logging lots of channels. These are:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Persistance.
  You don&#39;t need to keep old log files around if you wish your statistics
  to have a long history, thus saving you valuable file system space</para></listitem><listitem><para>Easily
  Customizable with stylesheets</para></listitem><listitem><para>Easily
  scriptable for processing many channels at once</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>

  <para>We have provided a sample shell script and Onis configuration file to
  automatically parse your log files in one go, producing the required output.
  </para>

  <para>LogServ is Copyright, 2003 by Justin Hammond.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Prerequisites and Installation.</title>

    <para>LogServ is designed to run on Top of NeoStats. The Following
    requirements at the time of writing are required for NeoStats:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>A
    Linux or BSD based Server or Shell.</para></listitem><listitem><para>A
    supported IRCd. Currently, Hybrid7, Unreal, Ultimate2.x or Ultimate3.x or
    NeoIRCd</para></listitem><listitem><para>Some basic Unix administration
    Skill</para></listitem><listitem><para>Of Course, a IRC network to connect
    it all together.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Spare disk space and a
    webserver to display the output</para></listitem><listitem><para>A log
    file parser such as Onis</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Please refer to the NeoStats website for more information on the
    requirements</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Compiling and Installation</title>

      <para>As long as you have successfully setup NeoStats, and installed it
      correctly, Compiling LogServ is very simple and straight forward. First
      you must extract the files from the download package. This is as simple
      as:</para>

      <screen>bash$<command> tar -xzf LogServ-&#60;ver&#62;.tar.gz</command></screen>

      <para>This should then create a directory called
      LogServ-&#60;version&#62; where &#60;version&#62; is the Version of
      LogServ. Then Proceed to Change into the LogServ directory, and run
      Configure as follows:<screen>bash$<command>./configure [--enable-debug | --with-neostats=&#60;dir&#62;]</command></screen></para>

      <para>--enable-debug is only useful for diagnostics purposes when used
      in conjunction with debugging tools. There should be no need to use this
      option on a day to day basis</para>

      <para>--with-neostats=&#60;dir&#62; should be used if your neostats
      directory is not in a standard location (~/NeoStats/). Replace
      &#60;dir&#62; with the full path to your NeoStats installation directory
      (NOT SOURCE DIRECTORY)</para>

      <para>Configuring LogServ will look something like the following screen:</para>

      <screen>[Fish@fish-dt]$ ./configure
checking for gcc... gcc
checking for C compiler default output... a.out
checking whether the C compiler works... yes
checking whether we are cross compiling... no
checking for suffix of executables...
checking for suffix of object files... o
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... yes
checking for gcc option to accept ANSI C... none needed
checking for a BSD-compatible install... /usr/bin/install -c
checking for pcre_compile in -lpcre... yes
checking Location of NeoStats...... /home/fish/NeoStats/
checking for /home/fish/NeoStats//include/dl.h... yes
checking Version of NeoStats...... Compatible Version
checking Whether to Enable Debuging...... no
configure: creating ./config.status
config.status: creating Makefile

(*----------------------------------------------------------*)
(| To compile your module, please type &#39;make&#39;               |)
(| If make completes without errors, then you               |)
(| Must &#39;make install&#39;, but please be sure that NeoStats    |)
(| Is not currently running with a module of the same name  |)
(| Running, otherwise Make install will not work            |)
(| !!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!! |)
(| If you are running a BSD, make install may produce a     |)
(| Error, if that is the case, then please manually copy    |)
(| opsb.so to the NeoStats/dl directory                     |)
(| !!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!! |)
(*----------------------------------------------------------*)
(| For Support please visit:                                |)
(|    IRC:                   /server irc.irc-chat.org       |)
(|                                   #neostats channel      |)
(|    WWW:   http://www.neostats.net/boards/                |)
(*----------------------------------------------------------*)
(|This Module was written by:                               |)
(|      fish (fish@dynam.ac)                                |)
(*----------------------------------------------------------*)
</screen>

      <para>If the configuration did not produce a error, you may then move
      onto Compiling LogServ. Compiling is simply just issuing the
      &#34;make&#34; command (or &#34;gmake&#34; if you are running BSD):</para>

      <screen>[Fish@fish-dt]$ make
gcc -c -O2 -Wall -g -ggdb -I/home/fish/NeoStats//include/ -I. logserv.c
gcc -c -O2 -Wall -g -ggdb -I/home/fish/NeoStats//include/ -I. log_processing.c
ld -shared -o logserv.so  logserv.o log_processing.o
</screen>

      <para>again, check for Error messages. As long as there are not error
      messages, &#34;make install&#34; will install LogServ, this README file,
      and any auxiliary files needed into your NeoStats directory:</para>

      <screen>[Fish@fish-dt]$ make install
/usr/bin/install -c -m 644 LogServ.so  /home/fish/NeoStats//dl/
/usr/bin/install -c -m 644 README.LogServ /home/fish/NeoStats//dl/../doc/
</screen>

      <para>If you receive *ANY* errors at all during the this process, please
      post them on our Support boards, at http//www.neostats.net/boards/</para>

      <para>Once Installation is complete, you can either configure NeoStats
      to load LogServ when it starts, or load LogServ via IRC.</para>

      <para>To Configure NeoStats to automatically load LogServ when it boots,
      add the following line to your &#34;neostats.cfg&#34; file in the
      NeoStats directory:</para>

      <para><command>LOAD_MODULE logserv</command></para>

      <para>To load LogServ via IRC, you must make sure you have the
      appropriate permissions and issue the following command:</para>

      <para><command>/msg neostats load logserv</command></para>

      <para>Thats it. LogServ is now loaded and ready for use </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Basic Configuration</title>

    <para>LogServ is completely configured online via IRC. When you first
    start up LogServ, it attempts some &#34;Sane&#34; defaults for you get
    started with, but you should always review these settings as soon as you
    install. There are a few important settings you may want to review right
    away. They are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>LogType is the format we should be logging as (Xchat, Mirc,
        EggDrop, or LogServ)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Logfile size to rotate at (1Mb by default)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Logfile age to rotate at (1Hr by default)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These are outlined below:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>LogType</title>

      <para>Logtype is the format you wish to perform your logging in. By
      default, LogServ logs using its own internal logfile format, but as of
      writting, no external logfile parser supports that format, so you are
      advised to change it. There are four possible choices:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>0 - LogServ Format. Our own Logging file format</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>1 - EggDrop Format. The Same logging format as the popular
          EggDrop Bot</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2 - Mirc Format. This is the same format as the mirc 6.0
          series</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>3 - Xchat Format. This is the same format as Xchat 2.0.5 IRC
          client</para>

          <warning>
            <para>Changing the LogType is imediate, and all new entries into a
            logfile will start with the new format imediatly. You should stop
            NeoStats, and remove the files in NeoStats/logs/chanlogs/
            directory after changing this setting, so when you next process
            your log files, it will not be confused by the changing formats.
            </para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Changing the LogFile Format</emphasis></para>

      <para>Before starting to log any channels, you should select which
      format you wish to log in. We recomend Xchat format. To change the
      LogType, issue the following command:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ set logtype &#60;type&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;type&#62; = The Logging format time, indicated by a number
      from 0 to 3, representing the differnt formats available as outlined
      above. </para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;logserv&#60; set logtype 3
-LogServ- LOGTYPE set to 3</screen>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Viewing the current Logtype setting</emphasis></para>

      <para>To view the current logtype selected, simple type:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ set list</screen>

      <para>And all the current settings (the rest will be explained later in
      this document) are displayed. The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;LogServ&#60; set list
-LogServ- Current LogServ settings:
-LogServ- LOGTYPE: 3 Log Type
-LogServ- LOGSIZE: 2000 Bytes
-LogServ- LOGAGE: 3600 Seconds</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>LOGSIZE SETTING</title>

      <para>LogServ stores logs in two places on your Shell. Live logs, or
      logs that are currently being written are stored in the
      ~/NeoStats/logs/chanlogs/ directory, and these the logs that are
      currently being updated. When the log reaches a certian size, or age, it
      is closed, and moved to a the ~/NeoStats/ChanLogs/ directory where you
      can process the log files. The LogFile size settings specifies how big a
      &#34;live log&#34; is allowed to reach before it is moved to the final
      directory. By default, LogServ will rotate all files larger than 1Mb,
      and this should be satisfactory for most users. </para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Changing the LogSize to switch at.
      </emphasis></para>

      <para>To change the size at which a logfile will switch at, use the
      following format:</para>

      <screen>/msg SecureServ set logsize &#60;bytes&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;bytes&#62; = if the file is larger than this size, it is
      &#34;swapped&#34;</para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;logserv&#60; set logsize 20000
&#60;LogServ&#62; LOGSIZE set to 20000 by Fish
-LogServ- LOGSIZE set to 20000</screen>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Viewing the current setting</emphasis></para>

      <para>Please refer to the previous section.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>LOGAGE SETTING</title>

      <para>In addition to the logsize setting above, LogServ will rotate a
      logfile after it has been opened for a period of time. This is so
      channels that might not have much activity still get a chance to be
      updated often.</para>

      <para>The logage setting can be changed via:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ set logage &#60;seconds&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;seconds&#62; = The number of seconds the log file must be
      opened for before rotating. Minium value is 5 minutes, but its
      recomended not to go under 1 Hour (3600 seconds)</para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;LogServ&#60; set logage 7200
&#60;LogServ&#62; LOGAGE set to 7200 by Fish
-LogServ- LOGAGE set to 7200</screen>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring LogServ to Log Individual Channels</title>

    <para>Obviously, we dont want to log every single IRC channel on the
    network, so you have to tell LogServ what channels you wish to Log. This
    is fairly basic. You have 4 options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add A channel</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Delete A channel</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Change a Channels settings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>View the Channel list. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Each Setting is described in the following section.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Adding a Channel</title>

      <para>Adding a Channel to be logged is instantanous, and the channel
      will begin logging straight after this command has complete. LogServ
      will join the channel, but not give itself any channel modes, so the
      channel owner can decide if it should be OP&#39;d or not. </para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ chans add &#60;name&#62; &#60;public&#62; &#60;url&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;name&#62; = The name of the channel you wish to Log. Must
      exist on the IRC network.</para>

      <para>&#60;public&#62; = Indicates weather to show the channel to
      non-privledged users in the channel logging list or not. Either the
      words &#34;public&#34; or &#34;private&#34;. If a invalid entry is
      specified, defaults to Public. Currently doesn&#39;t do anything.
      </para>

      <para>&#60;url&#62; = For informational purposes only. Displays the Web
      Address that users can visit to view the channel statistics. </para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;logserv&#60; chans add #ircop public http://www.neostats.net
&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used CHANS
-LogServ- Stats URL is set to http://www.neostats.net
-LogServ- Now Logging #ircop
&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish Activated Logging on #ircop</screen>

      <para>And the channel members of #ircop shall see:</para>

      <screen>--&#62; LogServ (LogBot@stats.dynam.ac) has joined #ircop
-LogServ/#ircop- Fish Actived Channel Logging on #ircop
-LogServ/#ircop- Stats will be avaiable at http://www.neostats.net when Logs are processed next</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Deleting a Channel</title>

      <para>Deleting a channel from LogServ means it will no longer log any
      activity in that channel. If the channel is currently active, LogServ
      shall part the channel, Close the &#34;live log&#34; and move it to its
      processing directory. </para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ chans del &#60;name&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;name&#62; = The name of a channel we are currently logging.
      </para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#62;LogServ&#60; chans del #ircop
&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used CHANS
-LogServ- Deleted Channel #ircop
&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish deleted #ircop from Channel Logging</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Changing Channel Settings</title>

      <para>You can change the URL location displayed when viewing the channel
      list using the chans set command. </para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg logserv chans set  URL &#60;name&#62; &#60;newurl&#62;</screen>

      <para>Where:</para>

      <para>&#60;name&#62; = The channel name you wish to alter</para>

      <para>&#60;newurl&#62; = The new URL you wish to set. </para>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used CHANS
-LogServ- Changed URL for #blah to: http://nowhere.com
&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish changed the URL for #blah to: http://nowhere.com</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Viewing the Channel List</title>

      <para>The channel list can be viewed by issuing the following command:</para>

      <screen>/msg logserv chans list</screen>

      <para>The output is as follows:</para>

      <screen>-LogServ- Monitored Channel List:
-LogServ- #blah (-) URL: http://nowhere.com
-LogServ- #bl (-) URL: None
-LogServ- #ircop (*) URL: http://www.neostats.net
-LogServ- End Of List.</screen>

      <para>The (-) or (*) indicate if the channel is currently active.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Misc Commands</title>

    <para>There are several other commands available. These are documented
    below:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>STATS</title>

      <para>The stats command shows some basic stats about the Logging
      Activities. With future versions its expected the amount of information
      will increase with this command. </para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ stats</screen>

      <para>And the output is</para>

      <screen>&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used STATS
-LogServ- LogServ Stats:
-LogServ- Monitoring 3 channels</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>VERSION</title>

      <para>This displays LogServ&#39;s Version number</para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ version</screen>

      <para>And the Output is:</para>

      <screen>&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used VERSION
-LogServ- LogServ Version Information
-LogServ- LogServ Version: $Rev: 19 $ Compiled Jan 13 2004 at 20:08:11</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>ABOUT</title>

      <para>This displays a brief message to users describing the function of
      LogServ:</para>

      <para>The Syntax is:</para>

      <screen>/msg LogServ About</screen>

      <para>And the output is:</para>

      <screen>&#60;LogServ&#62; Fish used ABOUT
-LogServ- LogServ logs channel activities to produce HTML pages describing some interesting Statistics
-LogServ- about that channel. If you wish to have your channel logged, 
-LogServ- please contact the Network Adminstration</screen>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>LogFile Parsers</title>

    <para>As mentioned in the introduction, LogServ only generates Log files,
    you still need to get some program to create the HTML pages from the
    logfiles. </para>

    <para>We currently recomend Onis for parsing the logfiles. You can obtain
    a copy of Onis from http://verplant.org/onis/</para>

    <para>We have provided a Sample Onis Configuration based on Onis 0.4.9,
    and a shell script that can be executed by Crontab to process all your
    Logfiles. This sample configuration and Shell script are installed into
    the ~/NeoStats/ChanLogs/ directory by default.</para>

    <para>This shell script will automatically go through each of the channels
    logs running Onis to update the HTML pages. At the top of the script are
    some variables that should be setup to configure where you wish to place
    the resultant HTML files, and where Onis is installed. You should read the
    begining of the file OnisDoLogs.sh to figure out what needs to be
    configured.</para>

    <para>This shell script assumes that you have a webserver on the same
    shell as NeoStats. If not, its upto the reader to implement some sort of
    FTP/SCP script to transfer either the logfiles, or the output from Onis to
    his webserver. </para>

    <para>Additionally, if you are using a different LogFile parser, other
    than Onis, you will have to develop your own script or method for updating
    the HTML pages. If you do develop a script for another Logfile Processor,
    please send us a copy, so we may include it in future versions. </para>

    <para>The logs for each channel are placed into their own directory within
    the ChanLogs directory, so if you are logging #neostats, The logfiles
    would be placed in ChanLogs/#neostats. </para>

    <warning>
      <para># is a special charactor on most shells and needs to be escaped.
      So if you wish to change directory to #neostats, you would actually type
      cd \#neostats. Keep this in mind when developing any scripts. </para>
    </warning>

    <para>Each Logfile is timestamped with the time it was rotated out of the
    logs/chanlogs/ directory, with the format &#60;name&#62;-YYMMDDHHMMSS.log</para>
  </sect1>
</article>